<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.4//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY copyright SYSTEM "copyright.xml">
 <!ENTITY % idcommon SYSTEM "common/common.ent">
     %idcommon;
]>
<refentry id="ref-zoom">
 <refentryinfo>
  <productname>Metaproxy</productname>
  <info><orgname>Index Data</orgname></info>
 </refentryinfo>

 <refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>zoom</refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>3mp</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo class="manual">Metaproxy Module</refmiscinfo>
 </refmeta>

 <refnamediv>
  <refname>zoom</refname>
  <refpurpose>Metaproxy ZOOM Module</refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>

 <refsect1>
  <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
  <para>
   This filter implements a generic client based on
   <ulink url="&url.yaz.zoom;">ZOOM</ulink> of YAZ.
   The client implements the protocols that ZOOM C does: Z39.50, SRU
   (GET, POST, SOAP) and SOLR .
  </para>

  <para>
   This filter only deals with Z39.50 on input. The following services
   are supported: init, search, present and close. The backend target
   is selected based on the database as part search and
   <emphasis>not</emphasis> as part of init.
  </para>

  <para>
   This filter is an alternative to the z3950_client filter but also
   shares properties of the virt_db - in that the target is selected
   for a specific database
  </para>

  <para>
   The ZOOM filter relies on a target profile description, which is
   XML based. It picks the profile for a given database from a web service
   or it may be locally given for each unique database (AKA virtual database
   in virt_db). Target profiles are directly and indrectly given as part
   of the <literal>torus</literal> element in the configuration.
  </para>

 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>CONFIGURATION</title>
  <para>
   The configuration consists of six parts: <literal>torus</literal>,
   <literal>fieldmap</literal>, <literal>cclmap</literal>,
   <literal>contentProxy</literal>, <literal>log</literal>
   and <literal>zoom</literal>.
  </para>
  <refsect2>
   <title>torus</title>
   <para>
    The <literal>torus</literal> element specifies target profiles
    and takes the following content:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>url</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL of Web service to be used when fetch target profiles from
       a remote service (Torus normally).
      </para>
      <para>
       The sequence <literal>%query</literal> is replaced with a CQL
       query for the Torus search.
      </para>
      <para>
       The special sequence <literal>%realm</literal> is replaced by value
       of attribute <literal>realm</literal> or by realm DATABASE argument.
      </para>
      <para>
       The special sequence <literal>%db</literal> is replaced with
       a single database while searching. Note that this sequence
       is no longer needed, because the <literal>%query</literal> can already
       query for a single database by using CQL query
       <literal>udb==...</literal>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>content_url</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL of Web service to be used to fetch target profile
       for a given database (udb) of type content. Semantics otherwise like
       <literal>url</literal> attribute above.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>attribute <literal>realm</literal></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	 The default realm value. Used for %realm in URL, unless
	 specified in DATABASE argument.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>proxy</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       HTTP proxy to bse used for fetching target profiles.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>xsldir</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Directory that is searched for XSL stylesheets. Stylesheets
       are specified in the target profile by the
       <literal>transform</literal> element.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>element_transform</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies the element that triggers retrieval and transform using
       the parameters elementSet, recordEncoding, requestSyntax, transform
       from the target profile. Default value
       is "pz2", due to the fact that for historical reasons the
       common format is that used in Pazpar2.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>element_raw</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies an element that triggers retrieval using the
       parameters elementSet, recordEncoding, requestSyntax from the
       target profile. Same actions as for element_transform, but without
       the XSL transform. Useful for debugging.
       The default value is "raw".
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>explain_xsl</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies a stylesheet that converts one or more Torus records
       to ZeeExplain records. The content of recordData is assumed to be
       holding each Explain record.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>record_xsl</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies a stylesheet that converts retrieval records after
       transform/literal operations.
      </para>
      <para>
       When Metaproxy creates a content proxy session, the XSL parameter
       <literal>cproxyhost</literal> is passed to the transform.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>element <literal>records</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Local target profiles. This element may includes zero or
       more <literal>record</literal> elements (one per target
       profile). See section TARGET PROFILE.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2 id="fieldmap">
   <title>fieldmap</title>
   <para>
    The <literal>fieldmap</literal> may be specified zero or more times and
    specifies the map from CQL fields to CCL fields and takes the
    following content:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>cql</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       CQL field that we are mapping "from".
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>ccl</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       CCL field that we are mapping "to".
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2 id="cclmap_base">
   <title>cclmap</title>
   <para>
    The third part of the configuration consists of zero or more
    <literal>cclmap</literal> elements that specifies
    <emphasis>base</emphasis> CCL profile to be used for all targets.
    This configuration, thus, will be combined with cclmap-definitions
    from the target profile.
   </para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
   <title>contentProxy</title>
   <para>
    The <literal>contentProxy</literal> element controls content proxy'in.
    This section
    is optional and must only be defined if content proxy'ing is enabled.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>config_file</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies the file that configures the cf-proxy system. Metaproxy
       uses setting <literal>sessiondir</literal> and
       <literal>proxyhostname</literal> from that file to configure
       name of proxy host and directory of parameter files for the cf-proxy.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>server</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies the content proxy host. The host is of the form
       host[:port]. That is without a method (such as HTTP) and optional
       port number.
      </para>
      <note>
       <para>
	This setting is deprecated. Use the config_file (above)
	to inform about the proxy server.
       </para>
      </note>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>tmp_file</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Specifies a filename of a session file for content proxy'ing. The
       file should be an absolute filename that includes
       <literal>XXXXXX</literal> which is replaced by a unique filename
       using the mkstemp(3) system call. The default value of this
       setting is <literal>/tmp/cf.XXXXXX.p</literal>.
      </para>
      <note>
       <para>
	This setting is deprecated. Use the config_file (above)
	to inform about the session file area.
       </para>
      </note>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
   <title>log</title>
   <para>
    The <literal>log</literal> element controls logging for the
    ZOOM filter.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>apdu</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If the value of apdu is "true", then protocol packages
       (APDUs and HTTP packages) from the ZOOM filter will be
       logged to the yaz_log system. A value of "false" will
       not perform logging of protocol packages (the default
       behavior).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </refsect2>

  <refsect2>
   <title>zoom</title>
   <para>
    The <literal>zoom</literal> element controls settings for the
    ZOOM.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>timeout</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Is an integer that specifies, in seconds, how long an operation
       may take before ZOOM gives up. Default value is 40.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>attribute <literal>proxy_timeout</literal></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Is an integer that specifies, in seconds, how long an operation
       a proxy check will wait before giving up. Default value is 1.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </refsect2>

 </refsect1>
 <refsect1>
  <title>QUERY HANDLING</title>
  <para>
   The ZOOM filter accepts three query types: RPN(Type-1), CCL and
   CQL.
  </para>
  <para>
   Queries are converted in two separate steps. In the first step
   the input query is converted to RPN/Type-1. This is always
   the common internal format between step 1 and step 2.
   In step 2 the query is converted to the native query type of the target.
  </para>
  <para>
   Step 1: for RPN, the query is passed un-modified to the target.
  </para>
  <para>
   Step 1: for CCL, the query is converted to RPN via
   <link linkend="cclmap"><literal>cclmap</literal></link> elements part of
   the target profile as well as
   <link linkend="cclmap_base">base CCL maps</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   Step 1: For CQL, the query is converted to CCL. The mappings of
   CQL fields to CCL fields are handled by
   <link linkend="fieldmap"><literal>fieldmap</literal></link>
   elements as part of the target profile. The resulting query, CCL,
   is the converted to RPN using the schema mentioned earlier (via
   <literal>cclmap</literal>).
  </para>
  <para>
   Step 2: If the target is Z39.50-based, it is passed verbatim (RPN).
   If the target is SRU-based, the RPN will be converted to CQL.
   If the target is SOLR-based, the RPN will be converted to SOLR's query
   type.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>SORTING</title>
  <para>
   The ZOOM module actively handle CQL sorting - using the SORTBY parameter
   which was introduced in SRU version 1.2. The conversion from SORTBY clause
   to native sort for some target is driven by the two parameters:
   <link linkend="sortStrategy"><literal>sortStrategy</literal></link>
   and <link linkend="sortmap"><literal>sortmap_</literal><replaceable>field</replaceable></link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   If a sort field that does not have an equivalent
   <literal>sortmap_</literal>-mapping is passed un-modified through the
   conversion. It doesn't throw a diagnostic.
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>TARGET PROFILE</title>
  <para>
   The ZOOM module is driven by a number of settings that specifies how
   to handle each target.
   Note that unknown elements are silently <emphasis>ignored</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The elements, in alphabetical order, are:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term id="zoom-torus-authentication">authentication</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Authentication parameters to be sent to the target. For
     Z39.50 targets, this will be sent as part of the
     Init Request. Authentication consists of two components: username
     and password, separated by a slash.
    </para>
    <para>
     If this value is omitted or empty no authentication information is sent.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry id="cclmap">
    <term>cclmap_<replaceable>field</replaceable></term><listitem>
    <para>
     This value specifies CCL field (qualifier) definition for some
     field. For Z39.50 targets this most likely will specify the
     mapping to a numeric use attribute + a structure attribute.
     For SRU targets, the use attribute should be string based, in
     order to make the RPN to CQL conversion work properly (step 2).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>cfAuth</term><listitem>
    <para>
     When cfAuth is defined, its value will be used as authentication
     to backend target and authentication setting will be specified
     as part of a database. This is like a "proxy" for authentication and
     is used for Connector Framework based targets.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term id="zoom-torus-cfproxy">cfProxy</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies HTTP proxy for the target in the form
     <replaceable>host</replaceable>:<replaceable>port</replaceable>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>cfSubDB</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies sub database for a Connector Framework based target.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry id="zoom-torus-contentConnector">
    <term>contentConnector</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies a database for content-based proxy'ing.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>elementSet</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies the elementSet to be sent to the target if record
     transform is enabled (not to be confused' with the record_transform
     module). The record transform is enabled only if the client uses
     record syntax = XML and a element set determined by
     the <literal>element_transform</literal> /
     <literal>element_raw</literal> from the configuration.
     By default that is the element sets <literal>pz2</literal>
     and <literal>raw</literal>.
     If record transform is not enabled, this setting is
     not used and the element set specified by the client
     is passed verbatim.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>literalTransform</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies a XSL stylesheet to be used if record
     transform is anabled; see description of elementSet.
     The XSL transform is only used if the element set is set to the
     value of <literal>element_transform</literal> in the configuration.
    </para>
    <para>
     The value of literalTransform is the XSL - string encoded.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>piggyback</term><listitem>
    <para>
     A value of 1/true is a hint to the ZOOM module that this Z39.50
     target supports piggyback searches, ie Search Response with
     records. Any other value (false) will prevent the ZOOM module
     to make use of piggyback (all records part of Present Response).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>queryEncoding</term><listitem>
    <para>
     If this value is defined, all queries will be converted
     to this encoding. This should be used for all Z39.50 targets that
     do not use UTF-8 for query terms.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>recordEncoding</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies the character encoding of records that are returned
     by the target. This is primarily used for targets were records
     are not UTF-8 encoded already. This setting is only used
     if the record transform is enabled (see description of elementSet).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>requestSyntax</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies the record syntax to be specified for the target
     if record transform is enabled; see description of elementSet.
     If record transform is not enabled, the record syntax of the
     client is passed verbatim to the target.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry id="sortmap">
    <term>sortmap_<replaceable>field</replaceable></term><listitem>
    <para>
     This value the native field for a target. The form of the value is
     given by <link linkend="sortStrategy">sortStrategy</link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry id="sortStrategy">
    <term>sortStrategy</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies sort strategy for a target. One of:
     <literal>z3950</literal>, <literal>type7</literal>,
     <literal>cql</literal>, <literal>sru11</literal> or
     <literal>embed</literal>. The <literal>embed</literal> chooses type-7
     or CQL sortby depending on whether Type-1 or CQL is
     actually sent to the target.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>sru</term><listitem>
    <para>
     If this setting is set, it specifies that the target is web service
     based and must be one of : <literal>get</literal>,
     <literal>post</literal>, <literal>soap</literal>
     or <literal>solr</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>sruVersion</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies the SRU version to use. It unset, version 1.2 will be
     used. Some servers do not support this version, in which case
     version 1.1 or even 1.0 could be set it.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>transform</term><listitem>
    <para>
     Specifies a XSL stylesheet filename to be used if record
     transform is anabled; see description of elementSet.
     The XSL transform is only used if the element set is set to the
     value of <literal>element_transform</literal> in the configuration.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>udb</term><listitem>
    <para>
     This value is required and specifies the unique database for
     this profile . All target profiles should hold a unique database.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry id="urlRecipe">
    <term>urlRecipe</term><listitem>
    <para>
     The value of this field is a string that generates a dynamic link
     based on record content. If the resulting string is non-zero in length
     a new field, <literal>metadata</literal> with attribute
     <literal>type="generated-url"</literal> is generated.
     The contents of this field is the result of the URL recipe conversion.
     The urlRecipe value may refer to an existing metadata element by
     ${field[pattern/result/flags]}, which will take content
     of field and perform a regular expression conversion using the pattern
     given. For example: <literal>${md-title[\s+/+/g]}</literal> takes
     metadata element <literal>title</literal> and converts one or more
     spaces to a plus character.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>zurl</term><listitem>
    <para>
     This is setting is mandatory and specifies the ZURL of the
     target in the form of host/database. The HTTP method should
     not be provided as this is guessed from the "sru" attribute value.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>
 <refsect1>
  <title>DATABASE parameters</title>
  <para>
   Extra information may be carried in the Z39.50 Database or SRU path,
   such as authentication to be passed to backend etc. Some of
   the parameters override TARGET profile values. The format is
  </para>
  <para>
   udb,parm1=value1&amp;parm2=value2&amp;...
  </para>
  <para>
   Where udb is the unique database recognised by the backend and parm1,
   value1, .. are parameters to be passed. The following describes the
   supported parameters. Like form values in HTTP the parameters and
   values are URL encoded. The separator, though, between udb and parameters
   is a comma rather than a question mark. What follows question mark are
   HTTP arguments (in this case SRU arguments).
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>user</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specifies user to be passed to backend. If this parameter is
      omitted, the user will be taken from TARGET profile setting
      <link linkend="zoom-torus-authentication">
       <literal>authentication</literal>
      </link>
      .
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>password</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specifies password to be passed to backend. If this parameters is
      omitted, the password will be taken from TARGET profile setting
      <link linkend="zoom-torus-authentication">
       <literal>authentication</literal>
      </link>
      .
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>proxy</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specifies one or more proxies for backend. If this parameter is
      omitted, the proxy will be taken from TARGET profile setting
      <link linkend="zoom-torus-cfproxy">
       <literal>cfProxy</literal></link>.
       The parameter is a list of  comma-separated  host:port entries.
       Bost host and port must be given for each proxy.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>cproxysession</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Session ID for content proxy. This parameter is, generally,
      not used by anything but the content proxy itself.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>nocproxy</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If this parameter is specified, content-proyxing is disabled
      for the search.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>realm</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Session realm to be used for this target, changed the resulting
      URL to be used for getting a target profile, by changing the
      value that gets substituted for the %realm string.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>x-parm</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      All parameters that has prefix x, dash are passed verbatim
      to the backend.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </refsect1>
 <refsect1>
  <title>SCHEMA</title>
  <literallayout><xi:include
  xi:href="../xml/schema/filter_zoom.rnc"
  xi:parse="text"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </literallayout>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>EXAMPLES</title>
  <para>
   In example below Target definitions (Torus records) are fetched
   from a web service via a proxy. A CQL profile is configured which
   maps to a set of CCL fields ("no field", au, tu and su). Presumably
   the target definitions fetched maps the CCL to their native RPN.
   A CCL "ocn" is mapped for all targets. Logging of APDUs are enabled,
   and a timeout is given.
   <screen><![CDATA[
    <filter type="zoom">
      <torus
         url="http://torus.indexdata.com/src/records/?query=%query"
	 proxy="localhost:3128"
         />
      <fieldmap cql="cql.anywhere"/>
      <fieldmap cql="cql.serverChoice"/>
      <fieldmap cql="dc.creator" ccl="au"/>
      <fieldmap cql="dc.title" ccl="ti"/>
      <fieldmap cql="dc.subject" ccl="su"/>

      <cclmap>
        <qual name="ocn">
          <attr type="u" value="12"/>
          <attr type="s" value="107"/>
        </qual>
      </cclmap>
      <log apdu="true"/>
      <zoom timeout="40"/>
    </filter>
]]>
   </screen>
  </para>

  <para>
   Here is another example with two locally defined targets: A
   Solr target and a Z39.50 target.
   <screen><![CDATA[
      </filter>
      <filter type="zoom">
        <torus>
          <records>
            <record>
              <udb>ocs-test</udb>
              <cclmap_term>t=z</cclmap_term>
              <cclmap_ti>u=title t=z</cclmap_ti>
              <sru>solr</sru>
              <zurl>ocs-test.indexdata.com/solr/select</zurl>
            </record>
            <record>
              <udb>loc</udb>
              <cclmap_term>t=l,r</cclmap_term>
              <cclmap_ti>u=4 t=l,r</cclmap_ti>
              <zurl>z3950.loc.gov:7090/voyager</zurl>
            </record>
          </records>
        </torus>
        <fieldmap cql="cql.serverChoice"/>
        <fieldmap cql="dc.title" ccl="ti"/>
      </filter>
]]>
   </screen>
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1>
  <title>SEE ALSO</title>
  <para>
   <citerefentry>
    <refentrytitle>metaproxy</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
   </citerefentry>
  </para>
  <para>
   <citerefentry>
    <refentrytitle>virt_db</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>3mp</manvolnum>
   </citerefentry>
  </para>
 </refsect1>

 &copyright;
</refentry>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: nxml
nxml-child-indent: 1
End:
-->
